你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到PWN学院
welcome back to pwn college
我是Yan，今天我们要讨论的漏洞利用场景是
I'm Yan today we're talking about exploitation scenarios
直接控制执行流之外的利用效果
and specifically vulnerability side effects
这里只是非常概况的讲一下
a very high level of this
需要在练习问题中具体深入了解更多
you'll dive more into this in the practice problems
当然这个模块会结合
of course this module we are putting together
我们在以前的模块中学到的一切
everything we've Learned in previous modules
今天的重点是
today focusing on basically
shellcode、内存损坏和以一种有趣的方式越狱
shellcoding and memory corruption and jailing in an interesting way
好吧，我的建议是
all right my advice to you
当你学习将这些不同的技术组合成端到端攻击链时
as you learn to combine these different techniques into an end to end attack chain
别忘了这一点
is don't forget that
通过内存损坏劫持执行流
control flow hijacking through memory corruption
不是你唯一能做的
is not the only thing that you can do
程序中有各种各样的漏洞
vulnerabilities in programs come in all shapes and sizes
并不是所有这些都能让你劫持执行流
and not all of them will allow you to hijack control flow
并不是所有的都是
not all of them are
其中一些能让你做的不光是劫持执行流这些
some of that will allow you to do more than just hijack control flow and so on
在内存错误模块中已经对此有了一些了解
you explored this a bit in the memory errors module
但现在
but now
这将变得越来越重要
this is going to become more and more important
特别是当你要在这节课中学会真正控制这些程序
as you learn to truly take control of these programs over the course of this module
我们来看一个鼓舞人心的例子。
so let's look at a motivating example.
如果你还记得沙盒模块的jail的话
we have a jail if you remember from the jail
等一下，我把摄像机关了，这样你就能看到
hold on let me turn off the camera so that you don't have to cause you
哦，好的，就是jail ...
oh yeah just jail da da da
如果你回想一下沙盒模块
all right if you recalled from the jailbreaking module the sandboxing module
这是seccomp沙盒，只允许我们读和写
this is a seccomp jail that will only allow us to read and write
这真是个坏消息
that's really bad news
我们打不开flag
we can't open the flag
如果光顾着利用
and if you hyperfocus on using this stack overflow
gets 提供的栈溢出来劫持执行流
that's provided to us by the gets to hijack execution
你最终会被困在这个沙盒里
you're going to end up in a situation where you're stuck in this jail
相反，你需要关注的是
instead what you need to look at is
gets还能让我做什么呢
what else does this gets allow me to do in this case
在栈上有一个结构
there's a structure on the stack
它有一个shellcode缓冲区和一个flag
that has the shellcode and a flag after the shellcode on the stack
这个flag表示shellcode是否应该在沙盒中执行
whether or not that shellcode should be sandbox
如果设置了该标志，默认是被置为1
and if that flag is set then at which is set by default
就说明要在沙盒中执行
then that sandbox is set up
所以如果用一堆a来溢出缓冲区，就会进入if分支执行
so if you overflow with a bunch of A's this check will pass
因为program.sandbox将是aaa
program.sandbox will be aaaaa
它表示真
that's of course it values to true and
在C中，任何非0值都为真
in C anything non 0 is true
最后导致seccomp被启用
and what ends up happening is the seccomp filters applied
让我们来看看它会是什么样子
let's take a look at at how that might look
我创建了这个sandbox.c
all right so I I created this sandbox.c
和我们在幻灯片上看到的一模一样
exactly what we saw on the slides
编译时允许栈可执行
and I compiled it and I compiled it with executable stack
因为我们需要在栈上使用shellcode
because we need to actually use shellcode on the stack
当然也
of course the same
可以创建不需要在栈上执行shellcode的示例程序
program could be created without the need to execute the shellcode on the stack
但这要简单得多，并且节约很多时间
but this is much simpler and save tons of life
好了,那么
alright so
我们可以获取一些shellcode
we can grab some shellcode
这是我写的一些shellcode
this is some shellcode that I wrote
这只是打开和发送文件
that just does an open and send file
我们就用它吧
so let's grab it
复制一下
and copy that
嗯，出了点问题
umm something wrong
哦因为复制了两行（引号闭合）
ah it copy across 2 lines
和
and
通过管道传给sandbox程序，不用n用e参数
pipe this through without n，e
表示在末尾添加换行符
so we want the new line on the end
这样gets读到末尾会停止
so that gets will actually termate
通过管道传给sandbox
and pipe it through sandbox
然后报bad system called
and says bad system called
因为我们试图调用open，但这不被沙盒允许
because we tried to do an open and it's not allowed by the sandbox
如果输入一堆a来溢出缓冲区
ah if we put a bunch of A's here to overflow the buffer
这会溢出我们的缓冲区
this will overflow our buffer
但系统调用会被seccomp拦截
but  we have a bad system call
如果shellcode只执行ret呢
if we for our shellcode just do a ret
然后放一堆a
and then we put a bunch of A's
你会看到
as you'll see
哦好吧，也报错了，因为程序退出试图调用exit
oh yeah because the program tries to exit
seccomp也被启用了
of course the seccomp filter is already applied
所以我们有麻烦了
so we're we're in trouble right
当然
of course
如果我们考虑一下程序逻辑
if we think about the program logic
不用A，而是用空字节去溢出
and instead of A's overflow with null bytes
那就能使这个检查失效，不启用seccomp
then that'll have a side effect of disabling this check
让我们来看看
so let's take a look
输入100个空字节
um I'm gonna put in 100 null bytes
一定有更好的办法
there's gotta be a better way
好完美
okay perfect
输入一堆空字节，它就成功了
put in a bunch of null bytes and it works
我们打开发送文件的shellcode成功执行了
our open sent file shellcode works
因为我们溢出了shellcode变量覆盖了sandboxed
because we overflowed this shellcode variable into sandboxed
并且是用null覆盖的sandboxed变量
and overloaded with nulls
内存损坏并不总是直接导致劫持执行流
memory corruption does not always lead to control executions directly
在这种情况下，程序已经提供了执行代码的机会
in this case the program already gave you code execution
但是您需要利用内存损坏漏洞
but you needed to use a memory corruption vulnerability together with that code execution
来禁用沙盒，再读取flag
to actually disable the sandbox and get the flag
好吧
all right
坏消息是，有些漏洞利用效果的副作用是很严重的
the bad news of this is that some side effects in a program are fatal
想一下这个例子
consider this example
你有一个shellcode
you have a shellcode
还有一个shellcode的副本
and you have a copy of the shellcode
shellcode副本存储在堆上的缓冲区
and the copy of the shellcode has an allocated buffer on the heap
用strcpy把栈上的shellcode拷贝到了堆上
that is strcpy into from the shellcode
这是个坏消息，因为当你要溢出这个shellcode缓冲区
this is really bad news because when you overflow this shellcode buffer
理想情况下通过栈溢出很容易
to then ideally overflow the stack and
将执行流重定向到shellcode中
redirect control flow into your shellcode
特别是如果所有的保护措施都没有，像1999年那样
if all the mitigations are disabled like it's you know 1999
不好意思，问题来了
sorry there we go
让我把视频移开
let me move that video
你会很难过
you're going to have a hard time
因为你会覆盖shellcode_copy指针
because you will overwrite your shellcode_copy pointer
很可能用的无效地址
most likely with something invalid
你的程序会在这里崩溃
and your program will crash here this strcpy
在这种情况下你必须小心
you have to be very careful in these scenarios
保持程序的状态，以便程序正常执行
to keep the state of the program viable for further execution
至少在目标实现之前
at least until you achieve your goals
所以在这种情况下
right so in this case
当shellcode溢出时
when you overflow shellcode
您需要用一个有效的地址重写shellcode_copy
you would need to rewrite shellcode_copy with a valid address
你们应该很熟悉这个
you're actually familiar with this
就像内存错误模块中需要在shellcode中修复金丝雀
with the requirement to fix up the canary in the shellcode in the memory errors module
这是类似的
this is analogous
记住这点
keep it in mind
当创建复杂的多阶段漏洞利用时
as you create complex multi stage exploits
或者多级攻击时
or multi stage attacks
那
that
有时候你的攻击必须非常非常小心
sometimes your attacks have to be very very careful
好吧
all right um
这就是我在这要说的一些副作用
that's all I'll say right now about side effect
你们会在练习题中探索更多
um you'll explore a lot more in the practice problems
祝你好运
good luck